[MUSIC]
[موسيقى]
Now that we've taken a deep dive into a linear classifier,
والآن بعد أن خضنا تجربة عميقة في أحد المصنفات الخطية،
namely logistic regression, let's jump into a different kind of classifier.
وهو الانحدار اللوجستي، دعونا ننتقل إلى نوع مختلف من المصنفات.
One called a decision tree, which is extremely useful in practice,
وهو واحد يدعى شجرة القرارات، والذي يعتبر ممارسة مفيدة للغاية،
especially when it combines with something called boosting,
خاصة عندما يجتمع بشيء ما يعرف بالتعزيز.
which you're going to see in an upcoming module.
والذي سنراه في الوحدة القادمة.
In this module, we're going to jump in to another really interesting real world
سننتقل في هذه الوحدة إلى مثال مثير للاهتمام آخر من الحياة الواقعية،
example, which falls more into the financial data modelling part.
والذي يندرج بشكل أكبر تحت الجزء الخاص بإعداد نماذج البيانات المالية.
It turns out that decision trees are extremely useful and
اتضح أن أشجار القرارات مفيدة للغاية
used a lot in the finance industry, so we're going to jump into something in that
ويتم استخدامها كثيرًا في مجال الصناعات المالية، لذا فسننتقل إلى شيء ما في هذا المجال
domain to give you a little bit more experience to that kind of data,
لإعطائك المزيد من الخبرة حول التعامل مع مثل هذا النوع من البيانات،
in particular when you look at evaluating loan applications.
وتحديدًا عند النظر في تقييم طلبات الحصول على القروض.
So lets say, I want to buy a house.
لذا، لنفترض أنني أريد شراء منزل.
I'm excited, I want to buy this particular house.
وأنا متحمس وأريد شراء هذا المنزل المعين.
To buy it, I don't have all the money, I need to take a loan from the bank.
ولشرائه، فأنا لا أمتلك المبلغ بالكامل، لذا أنا في حاجة إلى أخذ قرض من البنك.
So the bank is going to look at some properties of my history, like my credit,
وبالتالي، سيقوم البنك في النظر في بعض الخصائص بالسجل لدي، مثل الائتمان،
what has it been like in the past?
كيف كان في الماضي؟
How much money I make?
كم أجني من الأموال؟
How long my loan is of which time I'm willing to spend before I pay it off?
ما مدة القرض؟ وكم من الوقت الذي أرغب في قضائه قبل البدء في تسديد القرض؟
And other personal information about me, like my gender, age and so on.
وبعض المعلومات الشخصية الأخرى حولي، مثل جنسي وعمري وهكذا.
And he's going to take that information and
ثم يأخذ هذه المعلومات
try to make a prediction as to whether loaning me money is a risky thing or not.
ويحاول القيام بتنبؤ حول ما إذا كان إقراضي المال سيشكل خطورة أم لا.
So, let me give you a little bit more details on the kinds of things
لذا، دعوني أقدم المزيد من التفاصيل حول نوعية الأشياء
that people measure when they try to make loan application decisions.
التي يتم قياس الأشخاص بناءً عليها عند محاولتهم القيام بقرارات طلب القروض.
So typically, you look at credit history,
لذا، فهم ينظرون عمومًا إلى السجل الائتماني،
which looks at all the other loans I've taken in the past and my credit cards and
والذي يشير إلى جميع القروض الأخرى التي قد قمت بطلبها في الماضي، وبطاقات الائتمان
all that and have I paid those off on time.
وكل هذه الاِشياء، وما إذا كنت قمت بتسديدها في الوقت المحدد.
Then we look at my income, how much money do I make today?
ثم ينظرون إلى دخلي، وكم أجني من المال حاليًا؟
And we'll also look at what's called the term of the loan, which may be 3 years,
وينظرون أيضًا إلى ما يعرف بمدة القرض والذي يمكن أن يكون 3 سنوات
5 years, 15 years,
أو 5 سنوات أو 15 سنة
30 years, which is the period of time I'm going to take to pay back that loan.
أو 30 سنة، وهو يمثل الفترة الزمنية التي سأستغرقها لسداد ذلك القرض.
So, let's take a three-year loan means I pay back within three years.
لذا، إذا أخذت قرض 3 سنوات، فهذا يعني أني سأسدد هذا القرض في غضون الثلاث سنوات.
And finally, a look at information about the particular individual like my age,
وأخيرًا، ينظرون إلى المعلومات حول الشخص المحدد مثل العمر
whether married and so on.
وما إذا كان متزوجًا وهكذا.
So, given this information,
لذا، وفقًا لهذه المعلومات،
I want to make a prediction as to whether loaning me money is a risky thing or not.
أريد إجراء عملية تنبؤ حول ما إذا كان إقراضي المال يشكل خطورة أم لا.
So, a loan application system might look something like this.
ويمكن أن تكون أنظمة تقديم طلبات القروض مشابهة لشيء كهذا.
You get as input all the loan information that fill up a bunch of forms.
تحصل على جميع معلومات القرض التي تمت كتابتها ضمن مجموعة من الاستمارات كمدخلات للنظام.
It goes through a system if we have machine learning system or
ويتم معالجتها بداخل النظام، إذا كان لدينا نظام تعلم آلي
maybe minor created one.
أو نظامًا بسيطًا آخر.
Hopefully, machine loan system,
ونأمل أن يكون نظام تعلم آلي،
which is going to make a prediction whether this loan is safe.
والذي سيكون قادر على إجراء التنبؤ حول ما إذا كان هذا القرض آمنًا.
It's okay to make that loan or whether it's risky.
ما إذا كانت لا توجد مشكلة في إجراء ذلك القرض أو أن الأمر خطير.
So, some applications is going to be classified as safe while others will come
لذا، فبعض الطلبات سيتم تصنيفها كطلبات آمنة، بينما طلبات أخرى
in and be classified as risky.
سيتم تصنيفها كطلبات خطرة.
And the bank may be unevenly making loans to risky applications, but often
ويمكن للبنك على غير العادة أن يجري القروض للطلبات التي تشكل خطورة ولكن الأغلبية للطلبات الآمنة،
to save funds and we can view this loan application as a classification problem.
والآن يمكننا عرض عملية تقديم طلب القرض تلك كمشكلة في التصنيف.
I'm given this input information from my form and let's called the x,
سأقوم بإعطاء معلومات من استمارتي كإدخال، ولنسمي ذلك X
all information about me and my loan.
كل المعلومات حولي وحول القرض.
I pushed it through the classifier modelm which going to make a decision.
ثم أمررها خلال نموذج التصنيف والذي سيقوم باتخاذ القرار.
Let say y plus 1, y height equal plus 1, if it's a safe loan and
لنفترض أن y^ = +1 إذا كان ذلك قرضًا آمنًا،
y height equals minus 1 if it's a risky loan.
بينما ستكون y^ = -1 إذا كان القرض يشكل خطورة.
In this module, we're going to use what is called decision tress classifier.
وفي هذه الوحدة، سنقوم باستخدام ما يعرف بمصنف شجرة القرارات.
It might look a little bit like this, you start the application and
وقد يبدو قليلًا مثل هذا، أن تبدأ تشغيل التطبيق
look at some particular feature of the particular input.
وتنظر على بعض السمات الخاصة بهذا الإدخال المعين.
Let's say, what has my credit been like?
لنفترض أننا سننظر إلى حالة الائتمان لدي.
If my credit has been excellent,
فإذا كان تصنيف الائتمان لدي ممتازًا،
I just make the loan without looking at any other information about me.
فسأقوم بإجراء القرض دون النظر إلى أي معلومات أخرى حولي.
But if my credit has been only fair, I look at the term of the loan.
ولكن إذا كان تصنيف الائتمان مقبول فقط، فسأنظر إلى مدة القرض.
If the term is short, maybe it's too risky.
إذا كانت مدة القرض قصيرة، فربما يكون الأمر خطير.
But if the loan is long, maybe I'll take enough time to pay it off.
ولكن إذا كانت مدة القرض طويلة، فربما سيكون لدي الوقت الكافي لسداده.
Now if my credit is poor, I don't stop there.
والآن، في حالة كان تصنيف الائتمان سيئ، فلن أتوقف عند ذلك.
I look further where my income is even if my credit didn't pass being poor by
فسأنظر إلى حيث يتواجد الدخل، حتى إذا لم يتمكن الائتمان لدي من تخطي كونه سيئًا
making a bunch of money, maybe I'm willing to make a long-term
عند جني المزيد من المال، فربما أنوي إجراء
loan to somebody with poor credit that makes a bunch of money.
قرض طويل الأجل لشخص ما لديه تصنيف ائتماني سيئ ولكنه يجني ما يكفي من المال.
But if you don't make that much money and your credit is poor,
ولكن إذا كنت لا تجني هذا القدر من المال وكان تصنيف الائتمان لديك سيئ،
then you're out of luck.
فحينا سيكون قد نفذ حظك.
No loans for you.
لا توجد قروض من أجلك.
[MUSIC]
[موسيقى]